This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Digital Ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy, manage, and scale
applications of any size, removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love.
Digital Ocean stands out from the crowd
due to its simplicity, high performance,
and no billing surprises.
Join a community of over 3.5 million
developers on Digital Ocean. Sign up
with a free credit at do.co/seradio.
Hello, this is Jeremy Jung for Software
Engineering Radio. Today, I'm speaking
with Derek Collison. Derek is the
creator of Cloud Foundry, NATS, and the
current founder and CEO of Synadia. He
previously worked at Tibco, Google,
VMware, and Apcera. For much of his
career, Derek has been involved in
building messaging infrastructure for
applications.
I'll be speaking with Derek about
different messaging patterns, how they
fit modern applications, and his latest
project, the open-source messaging
system NATS. Derek, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio. Thank you, Jeremy.
Great to be here. First, I'd like to
kind of have a baseline. Uh could you
define what a message queue is? I could,
uh and I will, um but I think everyone's
definition is is probably slightly
different, and it's evolved. I mean,
these have have existed uh for quite a a
long time. And it's the notion of if two
applications are trying to communicate,
and at least in the older days, a lot of
times they weren't online, you know, at
the same time, they wanted to kind of
package something up and say, "This is
what I want you to process." So, when
you come online, please come here, pull
this thing off of this queue, and go
ahead and process that. And and there
could be multiple ones of us, kind of
like in a McDonald's line, that are
pulling from the queue of of new
customers coming in. But, I think that's
kind of the basis of what the original
queuing structure was. And it goes way
back to computer science structures and
stuff. But, they started to use that
pattern as a way for different processes
uh to communicate. And sometimes you'll
hear the term uh message bus. Is the
message bus the same thing as a message
queue, or is that something built on top
of a queue? How how would you define a
message bus? Yeah, so in the in the late
'80s, I think there was a a different
pattern that started to emerge in
addition to uh queuing, and that was
traditionally called publish-subscribe.
And it was specifically trying to solve
problems for very specific verticals
where uh instead of having a pattern
where I was trying to tell a whole bunch
of people about some set of of
information, let's say. Say a stock
price. And in the times before
publish-subscribe actually became
popular, the notion of And again, for
for the audience, this was on very very
slow networks compared to what we have
today, even compared to let's say LTE on
your phone. The gist of it was is I
would call you first, say, "Hey, price
of IBM is this." Hang up the phone, and
then I would just go down the line. And
it started become obvious that the line
was getting longer and longer. Trading
was becoming more and more popular. And
that as things were starting to speed up
and and algorithms were starting to take
place of of doing trades on their own,
so to speak. It was the very very
beginning of that versus a human that
the person in the front of the line got
a huge advantage over the person at the
end of the line, right? And so, the the
gist of what was trying to be solved
there is instead of going from a
one-to-one communication and I keep
walking down the line of everybody who's
interested, we would turn that into a
radio your
You would tune in to let's say the price
of IBM, the stock ticker would say it
once and everyone would get it similar
to like the old school uh radio
broadcast, podcast like that. Although,
these are on demand. Um and so,
what happened was is you had this notion
of queuing, traditional queuing that
came out of uh you know,
deeply rooted in computer science
structures and is a communication medium
mostly dominated by IBM and MQ series,
but there were others. And then there
was companies starting to evolve into
publish subscribe systems. And so, now
suddenly had a queuing pattern and you
had a publish subscribe pattern. When
you combine those two in some form or
fashion, and then we have to throw in a
little bit of notion of of quality of
service. And And the two that you know,
there's three, but the two that most
people deal with is at most once,
meaning almost kind of like a fire and
forget. Kind of like the way your brain
works. I'm going to shoot it out there
and if you catch it, great. And if you
don't, well, maybe you'll get the next
one. And then of course, there is
quality of service where it's at least
once, meaning I'm going to hold on to
it. I might put it on disk. I'm going to
wait for you to come online. Again, like
in more of the batch processing days.
And so, when you looked at queuing
methodologies, queuing patterns, pub sub
patterns, multiple qualities of service
including the third, which is exactly
once, which is a whole other show
probably on its own. Kind of putting all
those together and saying, "Hey, we're
not going to have a lots of these, you
know, Jeremy's going to have his own,
Darrel's going to have his own."
An organization or or possibly even
company wide, we kind of say, "No, we
have one of these." And that's kind of
what was determined to be like the
enterprise service bus. And everyone
kind of plugged into it. Kind of like uh
your nervous system, you know, a spinal
cord, so to speak. And they became very
popular for a while. And they still
dominate as an abstract pattern that
feels like the right way to go even in
today's landscape, but I think uh the
landscape today has changed so much that
the at technology has to change quite a
bit. And I we've seen that I think with
with entrance into what was very much of
rooted technology that
some installations technologies have
lasted 20 30 years
and to new entrants into this, you know,
which might not sound new to the
audience, but for for the people who've
been doing messaging for multiple
decades or so, um you know, Kafka's kind
of a new way to look at at the problem
and I think it's got a lot of deserved
attention about thinking about the
problem in a different way. And so it's
introducing new patterns to those pub
sub queuing, request reply, and then the
qualities of service that kind of made
up the technologies of the past. I want
to make sure we sort of define some of
the terms you used there. You kind of
went into at most once delivery. I'm
assuming that means that the message
will get to the subscribers at at most
once, but it may not get there at all.
Is that correct?
Correct. Yes. It's like most people call
it a fire and forget model, meaning
whoever's producing the data fires it
off and if you're not online or you miss
it because of an interruption somehow,
um there will be no attempts at
redelivery.
And it's actually a pattern that most
people skip over, go, "Ooh, I don't want
that. I definitely want to go down the
line and look at these others." But as
you start looking at systems and
becoming very much distributed in terms
of how many moving pieces there are and
looking at how you would build
resiliency into these, they're actually
ones that dominate the architectures
that I've been using, including the one
I used to build Cloud Foundry, at least
the control plane for Cloud Foundry. So
hopefully the audience will will not
just skip over, you know, that and start
looking at at least once or exactly once
semantics because I think there's some
great use cases where it's simpler, it's
more resilient, more predictable, and
you get actually a more resilient system
from the outside than you might expect.
Mhm. And I think I want to come back to
this since with NATS I believe you made
the decision to have at most once
delivery. The other thing you had kind
of talked about with a message bus
versus a queue, so what makes something
a message bus specifically, as you said,
was the pub/sub capability. So, it's
being able to publish a message and have
multiple people receive it, whereas the
queue was people would be kind of in a
line and would remove things one at a
time and only one consumer would get
each item. Is that kind of the correct
distinction? Yeah, I think that's fair.
Where I think I I was trying to direct
the audiences is that there was a
traditional queuing product, like an IBM
MQ series that dominated the landscape.
And then there was pub/sub technologies
like Tibco's Rendezvous, and there was
others. And then all of a sudden Tibco
came out with an enterprise messaging
system that had pub/sub and it had
queuing and it had request reply. And I
think, although Tibco was not the only
vendor in the space, I think that kind
of rooted the definition of what an
enterprise service bus might look like.
It's combining multiple patterns,
combining multiple qualities of service
all into one thing.
So, it's one infrastructure piece, so to
speak,
Mhm. that your application could kind of
pick and choose which pattern, which
quality of service made the most sense
for the application itself. So, we've
got the queuing, we've got pub/sub, uh
we've got request reply.
Request reply is really no different
than an HTTP call to a REST endpoint,
that sort of thing. Is that right? Well,
well, yeah. In terms of of a messaging
pattern, it's doing request reply. It is
trying to dominate on the pattern of I'm
going to ask you, Jeremy, a question and
you're going to tell me the answer,
right? And you can look at that as RPC,
request reply is HTTP, right? HTTP is
fundamentally a request reply protocol.
Every time you send in a a request,
you're going to get a 200 or 404 or 500
or whatever back. Um so, yes, that's
exactly it. Where
I think we could get into a discussion
of
these patterns is is that I think modern
systems, you know, have different needs
and wants as you transition from idea to
development to production and then going
through all the other arms of production
so to say regulatory, security,
compliance, quality meaning the SLAs and
things
where all of a sudden that pattern if
it's if it's the only pattern that
exists
really limits the ability to allow
production to kind of get their job done
as well. And so we can get to this but
talking with or talking about NATS and
kind of the original design concepts of
NATS was is to be a a technology that
could go from idea and multiple patterns
but then you pick one as a development
methodology but then it doesn't limit
production. It doesn't limit, you know,
the quality of service of the system or
monitoring or again regulatory or
compliance or security teams and I think
that's really important in in modern
systems of it's not only that you start
at the beginning with a basket of
different patterns and qualities of
service. You have to realize that as a
developer you're picking one to get your
job done. But that doesn't mean that's
the only job that might need to be done
with those messages, right? That we're
sending back and forth. I think that's a
a really important concept that I tried
to
communicate with engineers that that I
come across and and are asking well how
would you approach this or how would you
do this? And you know, before before we
officially started the call it's it's
definitely not an IQ thing. It's a scars
on the back type of thing.
But with the right technology it's
amazing how many of the friction points
you can reduce so that you don't whiz
through development, feel really good
about yourself and it takes six months
to actually get it deployed out into to
production. Those types of of things. I
I think a lot of developers who are just
starting out when they want to talk to
applications they're thinking more of
HTTP based calls like SOAP or REST or
they're thinking gRPC and so all of
these are very request-reply oriented or
RPC oriented. Can you give some examples
of uh some common problems that can be
solved by using a different messaging
pattern? Sure. So,
for the audience, let's let's make sure
we're kind of on the same page. As a
developer picks a request-reply pattern,
which by the way still dominates, right?
I do believe apps are becoming more
sensitive to doing eventing and doing uh
telemetry data and things that might
look more like pub/sub or streaming,
like right where
if you're looking at Kafka as a
technology. Where I think the difference
comes in with something like NATS and
there's other technologies that do this
as well, is is that request-reply is a
first-class pattern.
It just happens to be implemented with
pub/sub underneath the covers. And so,
what that means is is that the developer
says, "Well, yeah, I'm I'm sending a
request to Jeremy and I'm getting an
answer back. That's what I have to do,
right? That's what I am tasked to do as
a as a developer or an our systems
engineer."
And that makes total sense and that
pattern should dominate still a lot of
the interactions, whether it's async or
not in inside the app of "Hey, I'm
asking a question. I need an answer
back." Where I think the difference in
the approach that we've taken
might come to light is you say, "Great.
I know where Jeremy is. I send him a
request. I get a response back.
You know, everyone is is happy." Now,
when we move to production, it's like,
"Okay, tell me where I can find Jeremy,
right?" So, there's an issue of I need
to find Jeremy. And by the way, I
probably am not only talking to Jeremy,
I might be talking to 10 other
applications. So, now as I move into
production, it's like, "Okay, I got to
know where they are." Of course,
production's going to say, "Well,
Jeremy's really fast, but you know, John
over here, he might be a little slow.
So, now all of a sudden we want more
than one John."
But we don't want Derek to change. So,
we're going to tell Derek not where John
is, but where a load balancer is. So,
now there's this new process running.
And I think the audience this these all
will sound very familiar, right? So now
I'm sending to a load balancer instead,
it picks one of the Johns.
It understands state affinity if need
be, XYZ returns back. Now suddenly we
didn't do that for you, Jeremy, but now
we want to. Jeremy's becoming really
popular. Now suddenly Derek, the app,
might have to change, at least my
configuration has changed.
Now suddenly somebody comes in and says,
well, here's what we really want. We
want to watch all requests from Derek to
Jeremy. Most people say, well, that's
that's easy. You log everything and then
you move the logs into Hadoop and then
you analyze them and all this other
stuff. You add a sidecar, you add a
proxy, you add this, you add that. And
what you're doing is is that you're
you're asking production, I think, and
production and SREs, by the way, are
very good at this these days. They're
like, okay, I kind of get how to do
this. I know what I'm doing, XYZ. Then
of course there's the whole security
demand, which is, well, how do I
identify Derek? How do I identify
Jeremy? Is it the developer's problem or
is it the production problem, systems
problem? And where we looked at
something like NATS was is that we
wanted to transition and have Derek, the
app, and Jeremy, the application, the
back-end service, let's say,
not change, not even really have to be
reconfigured, and can move all the way
through this. So what's happening is,
and again, this is just a
a distinction around the big theme that
I've always talked to people about,
which is never assume what the message
that you send today is going to be used
for tomorrow.
So our dominant pattern is I'm sending
Jeremy a message, I get a response back,
and that's totally okay.
Within NATS though, that's a pub/sub,
meaning that if someone wants to come on
and say, hey, I want to run three
Jeremys,
you, the original Jeremy, and me, the
original Derek, don't change at all. We
never even stop running.
So operations, there's no, you know,
reboot, restart, change configuration,
anything. We just start three more of
them. So now suddenly there's not a load
balancer, there's not something else to
manage. All sudden it just kind of
works, and all sudden we're doing load
balancing, and we can scale up and down
at will, not dropping messages, and all
that stuff.
If security comes along or quality of
service comes along, meaning
not a a piece of technology, but a group
that says, "Hey, we need to make sure
that when Derek asks Jeremy something
that wh- whoever's fault it is, you
know, has to be in and out, you know, in
100 milliseconds, 200 milliseconds,
right? Google had these hard and fast
numbers of the request hits the front
door and it's got to be going back out
in
when I was there it used to be 200
milliseconds, right? Uh it was kind of a
hard and fast rule. With a technology
like NATS, a group can come along and
measure that all day long and again, you
and I have never changed, we've never
stopped running, we've never stopped
doing anything. And so now what happens
is is you look and you say, "Hey,
there's a dominant request-reply pattern
in development." But as we move into
production, right, the fact that those
requests and responses are also pub/sub
means we can attach any number of
listeners. They can be normal, they can
be their own queue. You can do
request-reply, you can do pub/sub, you
can do queuing all with the same
substrate and it doesn't kind of
box you in and limit you and especially
doesn't make production become more
complex, lots of moving pieces, right?
Cuz in dev it's like this was easy. It
was me and Jeremy. And I'd send him a
question, he'd send me an answer. Then
in production you go, "Well, there's
eight different things running around
just trying to support that one pattern
to do load balancing and logging and
collection of logs and security and and
uh compliance.
And so what we've seen is is that we've
seen a you know, complex problem become
more and more complex as you move from
the dev pipelines throughout and we
don't think that necessarily has to be
the way it has to be. If I can try and
break it down here, often a developer
will start with a request-reply pattern
over say HTTP, but if they were to move
that to a message bus such as NATS, you
would be able to have the discovery of
the clients be a part of the message
bus. So, if I want to talk to a service,
I don't necessarily need to know the
address or the name of that service. I
can send a message to uh to NATS, and
that can get routed to the correct
client. As a part of NATS, you can also
have load balancing. So, if I have 10
instances of my service, let's say I
have a service that's going to process
or resize an image, when I make the
requests to have this image I send
resized, NATS can actually handle the
load balancing and pick a service to
talk to for me, rather than me
introducing something like say Nginx or
HAProxy to choose the service to talk
to. Correct. And then, you also
mentioned that it is a request-reply
pattern, but internally, it's actually
using uh publish and subscribe. So,
you're
publishing a message into this message
bus, so that other services that are not
necessarily the target or the ones that
would be performing the work, they can
listen in and log out the results
without changing the software that's
talking to one another. Did I break that
down correctly? No, that's exactly
right. And and from doing it so long, I
I skip uh some pieces sometimes,
specifically about you know, I'm not
tying
Jeremy per se with a messaging system to
a host name or an IP, or the IP of a
load balancer, whatever that is.
Mhm. And I think there's still a
tremendous amount of value
where I think the value has even become
more obvious,
is that it's not only I tie, uh you
know, addressing and discovery to DNS or
IPs or whatever like that. We're also
now tying identity, right? And that's
what people naturally think of as
identity.
But I think it's really time for for the
groups at large that are really kind of
pushing the envelope and innovating uh
around distributed systems,
microservices, whatever you might want
to call them,
that we might want to take a step back
and say, "Hey, is that really the right
way we want to go? Do we really want to
have communications tied to, you know,
IPs and identities and security and off
C and off and models tied to IPs?" And I
think most people say, "No."
But we still kind of do it that way even
though our vision, I think uh
collectively of the world is is that
you know, computers and servers and you
know, resources like memory and
networking and stuff like that are
becoming very ephemeral, very fungible.
And
if we're thinking about how we want to
design a system
we want to be able to just use whatever
we want to use and be able to carry
along our identity and the security
constructs. And of course, how the
communication fabric can work has to be
the same, but it doesn't matter which
machine I'm running on. And again, I
I've been doing this a long time. So, I
do remember the day where I could walk
in almost any
uh you know, data center for for uh at
the time our customer set I could walk
down the right you know, hallway uh our
right aisle but between the server,
stop, look down and go, "Our stuff's
running right there." And I actually
still even know the IP, you know, what
it's supposed to be. We don't live in
that world anymore, but we really
haven't unshackled ourselves from that's
still kind of a main way we we use or or
apply security of communications and
identity. And I think it's it's a good
time for us to kind of take a step back
as an industry and say
I don't think that's what we want. And
we're kind of in a transition period now
where we're starting to move away from
it, but we've still got that one kind of
of link that's kind of holding us down.
If you take a look at more of a
traditional design of an application,
you might have a load balancer, and that
load balancer needs to be aware of the
IPs of all the services that can feel
that request. And you're sort of saying
like, "Maybe maybe that's not the the
right place or the right abstraction.
Maybe this messaging bus should take
care of who you can communicate with
rather than having sort of these extra
pieces you bolt on in order to provide
things like service discovery or or
basically just finding clients.
May- maybe we're we're not building the
functionality in the right place. Is is
that your opinion? So, what I think we
need is is this communication
infrastructures like the cell towers.
They're just ubiquitous. They're all
around you and yet they carry amongst
them as soon as you hook up to one
you're allowed to have an identity and
allowed to have these messaging patterns
that you that you have. And the
messaging patterns follow you around.
The identity uh follows you around. The
identity might not be just one thing,
right? It might be this application
running on this hardware representing
Jeremy.
And that has security and identity and
authorization primitives that can move
freely and they're just they're not
centralized. It's totally decentralized.
Um very very um you know, distributed
and but ubiquitous. And I think in the
old days people go, "Oh, message bus. We
got to run one big thing or maybe two
big things." And
and active passive or active you know,
hot hot mode type type stuff. And I
think
my hope for the audience is to to not
think of it that way. To think of it as
a always on ubiquitous
um kind of like the cell tower signal um
that you can just use and all of the
the things that you care about are taken
care of you without having to deal with
or really interact with from a
perspective of identity, security,
authorization type stuff with this
communications provider, right? We don't
we don't necessarily worry about the
cell tower having to be aware of our
credentials to log in to Gmail, let's
say, right? Gmail handles that and we we
interact with Google to figure what that
looks like and what that means.
Um and so I think there's a really
interesting opportunity to think of
things that way. So,
not the old message bus, not not by any
stretch, but this notion that
these things are everywhere. Matter of
fact, I could be sitting here and typing
something and it says, "Oh, I found one
right in your house." Right? It's in
baked baked into your router for Comcast
or Xfinity or Spectrum or Charter or
what do you have at least, you know, in
the the United States.
Um, and it just works, right? It it
found it, it has a link to it, it's
secure by default, and all the semantics
of the app that was working when I was
at the office, I was in the data center,
I was in my car, it's doing the exact
same thing here,
but its point of entry is actually in
the house. So, if I'm actually talking
to something in the house, it actually
never leaves the house. Right? It
doesn't trombone all the way to the
cloud and come all the way back.
And I think that's a powerful way to
look at it if the technology
uh, supports a lot of those things, if
that makes sense. Yeah, it sounds like
traditional messaging buses are centered
around a small set of powerful servers,
so you could get a situation where you
want to talk to a service that's located
in the same building as you, but you
have to send a request all the way to
this server and then it has to come all
the way back to your building. But,
looking to the future, uh, NATS instance
is a single go binary, so you got
limited resource requirements, so you
can have these instances running all
over the place, maybe in your office or
your home. So, you send a request to
your local node and that could get
routed to the service in your own
building rather than going through this
long path. We've been discussing about
how I can talk to Derek service without
knowing anything about Derek. Like, I
don't need to know your IP, I don't need
to know your host name, that sort of
thing. And the primitive that's used in
messaging systems tends to be a subject
or a topic. Could you kind of go into
what that is and and how that's used to
find services? Traditionally, people
have either topics or subjects. They're
usually comprised of multiple tokens
with some sort of separator, either it's
a slash or I always use a dot just
because that's what I've always used
historically. So, it'd be something like
foo/bar, right? Or or Jeremy/ you know,
request one, request two, whatever those
are. And many systems allow
you to express interest in things and
group them with wild cards. And wild
cards just kind of mean uh it's kind of
like a regex if a very simplistic regex
where you say, "Oh, I'm interested in
everything Jeremy's doing. So, I want to
listen to Jeremy/stars
or Jeremy.stars is what we always use.
Does Does it usually matter?" And so,
most systems use that as our addressing
space. So, we can bunch of or clump a
whole bunch of things together on with
wild cards. And an example around that
that might make sense for the audience
is if I have uh Jeremy.some_action,
I don't know, uh
create.you_know.customer_id
is is kind of a subject that's being
thrown around either as an event or
whatever. And I say, "I want to watch
all new creations of of customers."
Right? And so, I don't want to have to
say I want to subscribe to
Jeremy.new_customer.
whatever that customer ID is. I don't
know what that is. But I could say dot
star.
Right? And so, then I actually get the
real subject, let's say customer number
22.
You know, I can see that, but my
subscription was just one. And and
subscriptions, by the way,
um I think a lot of the audience
probably knows this, but they form that
interest graph, which is extremely
dynamic. And something you know, I've
been working on for over 20 years now.
Uh and I still don't necessarily have it
where I like it, but to be able to
optimize that interest graph and how you
actually propagate that such that when
someone sends to it, I know they know
that has to get to me is kind of almost
a a an art form. Everyone thinks it's a
a weekend project, and I can promise you
it's not. But that's the general gist,
right? There's these topics, they're
made up of multiple tokens. Most people
put them in hierarchies. Most companies
that decide, "Hey, we're going to go on
all in on this and we really care about
this and we, you know, whether it's an
old school enterprise service bus or
maybe something newer."
They usually spend quite a bit of time
trying to map out what that
topic hierarchy or that subject
hierarchy looks like so that we don't
step on each other's toes 2 years down
the line. And so it's a a very large
um
design process on how to try to set
these these up and it's it it it in
itself is an art form that that I've
seen lots of people do and and engage in
and and some are better than others, but
it always
was kind of a pain point to saying, "We
want this,
you know, this technology that we can
communicate with all of these back end
services for our org, but there's this
exercise that we can't skip. We got to
kind of think up front so that Jeremy
doesn't accidentally pick a subject that
Derek was using or a topic that Derek
was using and all of a sudden we're
stepping on each other's toes." And this
sounds very similar to the problems that
developers face when they're building,
say, a REST API where they have to
decide what are my, you know, endpoints
going to be, what are the functions
you're going to be able to call, how to
name your subjects or your topics.
Uh sounds like the same kind of problem,
the same kind of art. It is. And so what
they do is they, you know, exactly.
You're exactly right meaning they'll
they'll pick, I call it the the bottom
part of the tree, you know, what the
nouns and verbs and how you want to put
those together. And then as you move
from dev to test to production, that
kind of prefix changes, you know, and
and you can envision that as a, "Oh, I
have a totally different, you know, host
URL for my REST service." Or it's the
same host URL, but I have a
Jeremy and Derek has  Derek and
then we both have all the same verbs
potentially underneath. The same
exercise happens in in messaging systems
with with topic design or or or level
subject design.
Digital Ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy, manage, and scale
applications of any size, removing
infrastructure friction, and providing
predictability. So, developers and their
teams can develop faster and focus on
building software that customers love.
With thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community, we provide the
support you need. Digital Ocean stands
out of the crowd due to its simplicity,
high performance, and no billing
surprises.
Try Digital Ocean for free at
do.co/seradio.
What are some common mistakes you see
people make when they're they're trying
to design their topics? It's either one
of two things. One is is they don't
think hard enough about it and they they
step on each other very early on the
cycle.
Or they think so hard about it that
they've made something that's so brittle
that is resistant to better ideas coming
in
down the line. Right? Say, "Ooh, well,
maybe if we had actually kind of
constructed the subject hierarchy this
way, right? We could have used certain
pieces of information from the subject,
you know, being able to uh separate
those message traffic patterns out. Um
but now we can't do it cuz we're locked
in and everyone says you can't change,
you know, any of this. So, it's it's
usually one or the other. They don't
think hard enough about it or they think
too hard about it. But again, I think
there's opportunities where
the way people think about these
problems can radically change. There's a
messaging standard called AMQP that
systems like ActiveMQ and RabbitMQ use
to send messages to one another, but I
noticed that the more recent systems
such as NATS, Google Cloud Pub/Sub, and
Amazon Simple Notification Service all
don't support this. Why do you believe
that is?
Sure. And I I I can't obviously speak
for any of the the cloud providers. I I
can give an opinion not on how they
implemented their tech.
In terms of the protocols,
you know, we could have a whole show on
on protocols. Um I was very aware and
understood why AMQP became, you know, it
was
not in any small part actual reaction to
Tipco, right? And and their pricing
model which was, you know, beyond my
control at the time. But machines are so
fast these days and networks are so
fast.
All of the
massive amounts of bending over
backwards trying to, you know, squeeze
everything out with binary protocols
doesn't buy you much. And what it does
is it it it it constrains your
ecosystem. Very much like Redis and
Salvatore is a a good friend of mine and
I really
I've always been a huge fan of his and
what he's done
almost single-handedly, you know, with
with Redis. And so when him and I worked
at VMware together,
I said, Redis is a text-based protocol.
And he goes, yeah, he goes, I can make
it a binary, it won't make a difference.
Now, Redis is all request reply or most
of it's request reply. You can pipeline
and do things to speed stuff up. But for
NATS, when when I went and said I want
to build something just for me,
it's not going to bend over backwards,
it's not going to have all these
features, it's going to protect itself
at all cost. I just run a server and 90%
of the time that's all I have to do, no
config, it just figures stuff out. This
was almost 10 years ago. And it just
does everything is pub/sub and I can
layer on request reply and queuing and
I'm done.
And and what I did was I just didn't
have a lot of time, believe it or not,
to build this thing for for Cloud
Foundry. So the very first thing I did
was a protocol parser that was actually
just regexes in Ruby, believe it or not.
But it could do 150,000 messages a
second, which at the time was pretty
cool. Now, of course, you know, the the
NATS server has been written in Go since
0.52 of the Go language. You know, a
modern iMac now can do probably upwards
of 80 million messages a second with
NATS.
And we've never changed the text
protocol.
So
does it matter? You know, the the
protocol design is is an art form and I
still love it at at one level. Um but
what we did with NATS is is that because
the protocol is not only text-based, but
it's extremely simple. There's only a
handful of verbs that you need to know
to build your own client. And so our
ecosystem now is not constrained by the
only way a client can be born is if
somebody from the core team decides to
build one. We have a amazing ecosystem
of clients that you know, we never wrote
a single line of code for that people
can do and I think it's based on that
simplicity and the fact that it's as
text-based can get them started very
quickly, if that makes sense. When
architecting an application, you often
have a lot of moving parts. You were
talking about services communicating via
HTTP, and we recently did a show on load
balancing with HAProxy, as well as one
on service meshes with Istio, which uses
Envoy for its service proxy
functionality. It sounds like what
you're saying is
because these pieces can be complex and
may require a lot of ops work to keep
running, it might actually make more
sense to, rather than use all these
different pieces, to use a messaging
system like NATS, which can handle the
routing, the service discovery, the load
balancing, and be designed in such a way
that the ops overhead is very low. Is
that sort of what you have in mind?
Yeah, and exactly. And the the only
thing I would add on to that, and again,
this is kind of that aha moment that
that we had, was when we designed the
secure multi-tenancy, right? Think of
that as like a container for for
communications, messaging communications
for digital system service devices. When
we designed it, it was to power a global
utility, to power, you know, a single
URL that everyone could um tap into and
use and and feel like they're they're
isolated. It's it's their own container,
their own sandbox, meaning Jeremy, you
get a sandbox, right? And you every
message you send, regardless of how you
address it, topic, subject, whatever
that is,
only the people that are also in your
container, your namespace, whatever you
want to call that. Uh we call them
accounts. Um
uh can see any of those messages.
And again, earlier in the the the talk,
I talked about but I want to promote
sharing.
Where the massive opportunities and
power of
the World Wide Web and the internet and
the global cellular network have really
rooted on is is that if we wanted to
talk, we didn't have to do anything
besides start talking, right? We were
already kind of connected.
And so we did that and we we designed
this notion of saying, well, you have
your own little sandbox and you
communicate in there.
And you control everything in that
sandbox.
And you can import things into that
sandbox. So I could import, you know,
Derek and he has a service and I can
send him a request to it and he sends
me, you know, what's 1 + 1 and I'll send
you two back. You know, very simplistic,
but for for the sake of the
conversation. And you've imported that
into your sandbox and you put it
anywhere you wanted to.
You meaning you control that. So now, if
if the audience remembers back to the,
you know, big grand design of subject
spaces and topic spaces and people
either did too little or too much, now
suddenly it's now there is no design
stuff. You can actually say, okay, I
have internally in my little sandbox for
Jeremy, I have this one subject and I
have this other subject and then I'm
importing Derek and it's on
Derek request.
And you define that. It does not matter
what you call it. It's your world,
right?
And that's how you import things. Now,
eventually you kind of go, "Ooh, I
finished. I want to put my service or
this stream out to the world. So I'm
going to now export it, right? So I'm
exporting this thing and you might need
permission and that's okay. You'll
figure out how to get permission from
me. But now all of a sudden what we what
we've realized is that people who were
designing these systems, and again, they
went through a pattern. We want to
innovate. We want a new tech. We don't
want the old stuff. Let's pick something
new. Let's do POCs. Let's try not to be
a silo. Let's set up a big service. Wow,
that really didn't turn out the way we
wanted to. Crap, let's go back to the
silos.
When they look at something like NATS,
which again is is exist today now with
these technologies, they go, I just
click a button and you have your sandbox
in less than 2 milliseconds cuz I don't
care what you do on it. And if you want
to start importing stuff, let's say from
Derek, that's between you and Derek. I
don't care as a company organization dev
test prod even. It really doesn't
matter.
As soon as Jeremy goes, okay, I'm ready
to export.
We've had multiple users and customers
now go, this is perfect cuz that is your
defined interface. That's your
microservice. That's exactly what that
is. It's It's how I would import it, how
I would send a request, what the
response looks like. All of that's kind
of captured in that very simple
primitive of and I wish I was smarter
than than than our design, you know, was
just to make sure that they're isolated
by default. Everyone's like, that's
perfect. I don't have to design subject
spaces because I can export it as
Jeremy one and Derek can import
it as  Jeremy's cool service
request 45 or whatever. Or
stream, you might be a really cool
stream that I want to import from you,
you know, the like events and and data
and and streaming data type stuff. And
the cool thing is is that when you get
to that point and and we're watching
customers go, this is great. Every
little business function, microservice,
or whatever, they get their own little
sandbox. They import whatever they need
to get their job done and then once
they're ready to export their own
version of our, you know, our cool
streamer service, they do an export,
there's an audit real quick from
security and stuff. And what happened in
in so many of these customers already is
the security team comes in and they
usually have a look on their face like,
this isn't going to go well for you.
And they look at the tech and they go,
huh. They actually thought really hard
about secure by default, no private keys
or passwords are ever given to the
system whatsoever. We anonymize
requests, so I know I got a request from
someone who's authorized, but I have no
clue who it was from.
Those types of things keep reducing that
friction point that I was talking about,
not only from a dev perspective, but ops
and security and regulatory and things
like that. And again, I wish I was smart
enough to know that this was was coming,
but it's essentially defining the way
communications work in this new world
where there's service meshes and
microservices, but in a very different,
simple, secure by default way.
Hopefully, that makes sense. I want to
make sure I understand the way that
you're using subjects or topics in this
design. You were describing how you
would have a subject and it could be
Derek/image
service/two or something like that. And
you said that you have sort of your
private, I don't know if you would call
it a name space, but you have like the
names that your system understands, but
somebody who wants to talk to that
service, they would be able to import
that subject or that topic with a
different name. I was kind of trying to
follow how exactly that worked. No,
that's exactly right. Meaning, when we
give you that sandbox of communications,
you control everything that's in that
sandbox, not just the stuff you're
designing, but the things you import.
And so, let's say I have, so, you know,
imageprocessor.request,
whatever that is. And I just call it
ip.req. I like little short things. So,
that's all I call it and and I'm
running. And I want to go into
production. I say I'm going to export
this thing. Production says, "Okay, we
don't care where you are running this
because when Jeremy comes along and
says, "Hey, show me the list of stuff
that's available." Oh, Derek has this
cool service called, whatever, but it
has a description, it has, you know,
open API link that shows that it's the
request looks like this, response looks
like this. And you go, "Great. I'm going
to import this." He needs permission,
he's going to give me a token that
allows me to do it. But when you import
it, you put it wherever you want. So,
you could pick whatever subject you want
inside of your sandbox
and you send a request to that subject
and I magically get it on mine. But,
it's totally secure. It's always
buttoned down. It's always auditable.
It's always, you know, all these things.
And then, of course, I get it. I see it.
And you sent the reply subject to me.
But, this reply subject isn't the one
you sent and it's totally anonymous to
me. I've no clue what it is. But, when I
send the message the response to that,
you get the answer.
And so, now the these groups, again,
whether it's a serverless or
microservices or just an org, they
control everything in their sandbox. So,
now all of a sudden, instead of having
that 4-day long topic / subject design
session, it's like we can sit around at
lunch and figure out and and make these
very, very short. We don't have to have
like a
I'm not picking on Java, but like a Java
variable name that's camel case and has
eight eight humps, you know, and it goes
takes up 40 characters or whatever. And
so, now all of a sudden, it's extremely
simple. And what's interesting as an
observer
an observer looking at you and I
they can easily say, "Oh, Derek depends
on these three things cuz those are what
he imports. And Jeremy depends on Derek
cuz he's importing his service."
And Jeremy can run anywhere he wants, as
many of them as he wants. Derek can run
anywhere he wants, as many as he wants.
But, it's locked down meaning we know
that someone who's sending the request
is authorized by the Jeremy sandbox, the
account that has users that have their
own permissions. So, you might have
users that can send to the service and
others that can't. So, all of this stuff
just kind of works together and it's
easy. And it's by default. It's not like
you have to go into ops and say, "Well,
how long is it going to take you to bolt
this stuff on and make it secure and
understand TLS or whatever that that
construct is and then prod has to do all
this other stuff." It's No, my
development from day one, the very first
message I sent was already secured. We
haven't got there yet, but we also
believe that if we could say a user of
the system says,
"I actually want I want this system like
a zero trust system. I don't want to
trust it at all.
Of course, it might not route my message
where I want, but also, no matter what
I'm sending it, it cannot compromise me
or understand anything about what I'm
doing. And we're not there yet, but
we're closer than people might think.
And so, then if you combine these
accounts in your own little sandbox, you
manage everything inside there, so it
makes it very easy. And then there's
there's these things, exports and
imports, to define how we talk between
those interfaces, let's say, right?
And then you look at this notion of, oh,
and I can use a global utility, any
cloud provider just works. Same URL will
pin you to the AWS East region, cuz
that's where you're you're running. And
if I want, I can run a server that has a
little server, you know, a NAT server,
same as the other ones, but again, you
start up, it starts up instantly, no
config or extremely low config, and it
can transparently
join this global network in a way that
it's zero-trust. So, I can be talking to
my own little server in my data center,
but then I got to reach across to, let's
say, Europe and talk to Germany. It just
all works. It's all secure. It's all
auditable. It can be even run in
zero-trust mode. That, I think, makes
people think a lot differently about how
they might solve the problem. The
problems aren't necessarily different,
right? We're still trying to decompose
software systems, make lots of little
pieces, but we just don't want the lots
of little pieces to be painful to stand
up, to develop, to
operate and maintain, right? But if it's
easy to do that, it makes sense, right?
Do lots of little pieces and then, you
know,
uh of course, there is a a systems
engineering component where you're like,
yeah, you we should combine these for
mostly latency reasons, right? We want
the experience is that you get it in
10 milliseconds, not 180, because it's
five microservices talking over HTTP
through load balancers, ping-ponging
back and forth, right? And I think
eventually, you have to pay the piper,
um and I think a lot of these
microservice service mesh technologies,
where the complexity is just so high,
eventually people are going to say,
"Hey, is there something simpler,
you know, that that that we can
potentially use?" And we hope we might
be a part of that story.
Hoping that making the communication be
this solved problem, uh the security,
multi-tenancy, the sharing, have that be
handled, and that way you can think
differently about how you design your
services where you don't have to worry
about the complexity of adding an
additional service, and you're kind of
talking about the latency that might
come in as you you bring in the load
balancer and go through HTTP and all
these different pieces. Um how this may
hopefully encourage you to
design your applications differently.
Yeah, and and to be quite frank with
with you and the audience, you know,
when we were looking at where are the
potential business models for something
like NATS, um one is you know, oh, we
could run it as a service. But that was
a a a massive failure. And and the
reason it was a massive failure is if
you are truly treating it as a silo
technology just for you,
running NATS is usually you click a
button or run a Docker image, and
we have a lot of users who really love
the technology and and love how
responsive we are,
but they're not going to pay for us to
run it cuz they just run it. They don't
even monitor it. You know, one of our
customers said, "Well, we have these
major events every 2 years, and that's
when we decide if we want to upgrade or
not."
And I said, "So, you don't even monitor
it? You don't even" They go, "Nope. It
just sits there. Never It just works.
You know, we like that." But for us,
that presented a a massive thought
exercise challenge around, well, they
don't want to pay for support cuz it's
so easy, and they don't want to pay us
to run it as a singleton.
Is there any opportunity around software
that's just easy
to to generate a business around? And
but I wouldn't go back on that. In other
words, I wouldn't go back and try to
make it more complex and and bug you so
that you're going to
uh pay me. And so, you know, the the
team that kind of maintains it, we're
not a large team, but we have
a lot of people who've been doing this
stuff for a long time, and they take an
incredible amount of pride in the fact
that it just works, and it's really easy
both to start, you know,
I put up a demo server about 4 years
ago, and it still runs, and we see
people use it all the time. So, our
getting started thing is take a client,
which are very small, you know, we
I think we do 34 languages now,
something like that. And if you want,
just point to the demo server and knock
yourself out. And they go, "Okay, well,
what if I want to run my own server?"
It's like, "Well, just now Docker is so
ubiquitous from a
development uh you know, on most
people's machines." It's like, "Well, we
have a Docker image, so you can just
kind of go Docker run this." And they
go, "Perfect." And then we never hear
from them again.
You know, or we hear from them in far
and between, like months, and they go,
"Okay, now I want to run a small
cluster." It's like, "Okay, here's, you
know, uh the Docker command, or here's
the NATS operator, or here's how you
might do it, you know." And again, they
go, "Wow, this is so easy." And we're
like, "Good, that's that's
that's what we want, but we also think
that's what we want to see in stuff that
we use, too. It's not only easy to get
started, it's easy at the end of the day
running something in production, and
that's not a that's not always a trivial
thing to try to hit on all of those
cylinders, and we are by far from from
perfect, and there's a lot of other
great tech out there that does it better
than us, but we think the trends are
going to be moving towards, you know, I
want to think about the problem in the
same way, but give me the tools and
technologies that are that are vastly
simpler. They don't make my life more
complex and add more complexity. If
somebody was building an application,
and the the example I want to use
because I believe you you did a lot of
work with financial systems at Tibco.
Let Let's say I had a a trading system,
and I wanted to receive uh live prices,
so like my my clients are kind of
getting the updates of the the different
stock tickers.
And I want to be able to store a history
of, you know, all the prices of all
these stocks.
And, um, and I want clients to be able
to to buy or sell, and they need to be
able to not have like duplicate
operations or or lost orders. So, I kind
of wanted to see like
how would you build a system around that
given the sort of features that NATS has
and the features that it doesn't have.
Like, for example, how,
um, you've described how NATS has
exactly once delivery, or sorry, not
exactly once. Um,
at most once delivery. So, there's no
guarantee that like my order would get
to, um, you know, the exchange, things
like that. So, if you could maybe kind
of walk through that. Sure. And just as
of note in the
you know, early, mid, late '90s, those
systems cost tens of millions of
dollars. So, we'll try to walk through
Yeah, you've essentially just defined a
a full-on trading desk, uh, and and
developing software for that was, uh,
paid very handsomely at, uh, I still
think to to this day. So, there would be
the notion of, you know, there's a
stream now. Uh, we call them Uh, by the
way, NATS, um, as a a project, uh,
includes both at most once and at least
once. But, I call it Stan. Most people
know it as NATS streaming, which gives
does give you at least once. But, the
way we would do the the the stock quote
part would be we're just sending out,
you know, on, let's say, nyse.whatever
the ticker symbol is and
nasdaq.tickersymbol. And, uh, we have
our own account that we talked about
before.
We export those two. And you can import
them, but you need an authorization
token for us. And that's all handled and
easy. Just make sure that I will
authorize Jeremy to receive the Nasdaq
ticker. So, me myself
because of the way networks are and
they're fairly efficient is I would not
make it anything but at most once. It's
fire and forget. If you miss it, you
probably want the newest one when you
come back online, not spend 10 seconds
going through all the old ones. I think
that's an anti-pattern.
So, that would be fire and forget to all
of the clients. Okay.
because again semantically, do you want
me to give you every update or you want
the you want to know at this point in
time I'm connected, I have a green dot
meaning I'm I'm good, and I know that
Google's price is this or Tesla's price
is this. But, I would put it in its own
account. That means Jeremy, as you're
importing it, you have to get
permission. So, we know there's that
security piece there that you are
allowed to do it. By the way, these
security things are JWTs, ED25519 keys,
have expirations. They have all these
things that people want from a security
and production side, and you as the
developer don't have to think about
that. Just It all is there, just works.
So, now you can import it. Knock
yourself out. Now, let's say you,
Jeremy, also want to save all of this
stuff. And you want to have your own
kind of historical stuff cuz you might
want to start looking through it and
analyzing it, maybe putting some machine
learning on it, you know, maybe trying
to start a hedge fund. So, what I would
say there is is once that stream
actually enters into your
sandbox, your your account, that you
will have your own NAT streaming system,
which you can think of it like Kafka,
right? It just stores a a serialized log
of of messages, and then you would store
them that way, and you can retrieve them
through STAN 2 say, "Ooh, I want to
create a new application. I want to
start from the beginning of time." Or I
want to start an hour ago. Or I only
want to see Tesla stock or or Google
stock. And you can do all of that by,
you know, running this service inside of
of your account for the ones that you're
saving. For the trading desk, meaning
you want to do a
trade, let's say. Again, there's some
interesting
ways to approach the problem. But, in
general, you want to import a service
that if you send a request to, you get
an answer back saying, "Got you. You're
good." right? I I I sold your Tesla
shares or I sold your Google shares or
bought Apple for you, whatever those
things are.
And again, just knowing that these
things cost tens and you know, even more
sometimes, millions of dollars in the
path to design, today if I was using
that to do that, again, most people
would say, "Aha, now I know you're going
to have to use at least one semantics
here." And I say, "Actually, I don't.
I'm sending a request reply."
Right, Jeremy? You're sending a request
me saying, "Please sell this and let me
know if you're good to go." Now, I could
do something where I put it in a
database or I mark it somewhere else
because the trade settlement and the
execution happens asynchronously, right?
Meaning, I'll tell you, "Okay, I got
your order." and then I'll ping you back
later when it's actually, you know,
finalized. And then this used to be T3,
T plus 3, but now it's T plus 1, I
think, or maybe even less. Meaning, the
official settlement takes a day and
you'll get a email or whatever. But
again, I probably wouldn't use something
like a a Kafka or even NAT streaming
to send that request because you want an
answer back and you're online, right?
You're you're there. And adding some of
that sometimes is an anti-pattern,
especially if you're always doing
request reply.
And and you can think of this as, you
know, people kind of look at me and I've
had people, you know, and and this is
their earnest, you know, honest opinion.
They're like, "Derek, you just don't
know what you're talking about." But
I've kind of have done this for a long
time and I always say, "Look at the web.
If you click on please deposit 100 bucks
into my Wells Fargo account." And all of
a sudden the page goes blank. What do
you do? And I say, "What you don't do is
you don't walk away."
Right? You go uh reload, reload, then
you might check your balance, see if it
had appeared. If it didn't appear, you
do it again, right? And so I I believe
in those types of patterns. Surface that
stuff. Law of leaky abstraction and
things like that. Some of the worst
system outages I've ever seen in my
career, believe or not, are from a
message being re-delivered because you
told the system hold on to this and make
sure Derek gets it. But Derek, meaning
me,
it had no semantic meaning outside of
let's say 5 minutes. But you were you
got you you delivered it to me an hour
later and I just puked. Right. You know,
the whole system cascaded down type of
type of deal.
And so a lot of times those things you
think it's like, oh, I absolutely need
this, you know. I absolutely need, you
know, not only at least once, I need
exactly once, I need distributed
transactions. And what we've seen with
modern systems is they're going away
from that complexity.
Cuz a lot of times when something goes
wrong, you still don't know necessarily
what to do.
You only know that if it says it's good,
everything was good and you're usually
very, very slow. You can't handle a lot
of those things at all. We we had a
customer who who was trying to project
out 5 years in terms of load and and
they wanted exactly once messaging and
distributed transactions. So the
messages What that means is the messages
are coordinated with another resource,
uh like a database through a uh formal
protocol, uh usually XA.
And we did it and we implemented it and
I looked at the person I said, I promise
you you'll ask me you'll come back and
not use this, you know, in a short
period of time. Um and they did. And we
came back and we said, we would do a
model where we would use at least once,
uh meaning we're going to try to deliver
this thing, you know, short TTLs, the
ability to dedupe, uh and then
compensating transactions. No XA type
stuff, but we can compensate meaning if
we got the message and we tried to do
the database, but it failed, we'd know
how to kind of unroll that, right?
Anyway, long story short, that system
now has been running 23 years. And so,
it was a lot simpler. It wasn't what
they thought they they wanted, but they
said it was one of the best investments
they ever made because of the longevity
they got out of the system. Now, of
course, they tweaked it and upgraded it
and made, you know, more machines, more
powerful machines, of course. But for
something to run that long, you know, is
that's that's I like that. That gives me
a great amount of satisfaction as a a a
technology person. But again, all of the
things that the
customer thought they needed to solve
the problem really turned out not to be.
And so that's how I do that. So we've
got the stream, but it's not a stream,
it's a fire and forget into Jeremy for
the the stock quotes, but it's
authorized, so you know who So you can
audit and say, "I know exactly who's
allowed to watch the Nasdaq ticker
symbol, right?" And who's not. Um I mean
I can charge them for or I can
internally bill them for it. You on your
own, regardless of what I'm doing, can
keep a stream of all of those, process
them at will, any way you want. And then
of course doing the trades themselves, I
would not say put this in a messaging
system and it's the one that guarantees
that the order gets processed. It's
you send me a request, I stamp it in
whatever a database or whatever. I I I I
don't believe in
putting everything into like a message
stream. That's not my my go-to
architecture, but I mean databases have
been around a long they work, they're
good, you know. So whack in the
database, but once that's done then I
send you an okay going, "Hey, you're
good to go. I have your order." And that
might take, you know, tens of
milliseconds, hundreds of milliseconds,
hopefully if it's a well-designed back
end. But on the messaging front, because
you're doing request reply, I don't need
anything except at most once. And so
you something like, you know, the the
global utility or whatever that is
secure and you can do it a zero trust.
I'm just asking the messaging system to
give me identity and securely, you know,
deliver a message to the trading desk,
wherever that is, and it can keep
changing and it doesn't matter. And you
can keep moving, right? You got your
laptop in Europe, now you're back in
North America.
And so that's
very
quick nutshell of of how I would
approach that today. And what I think
the audience will be surprised at is is
that I didn't say, you know, at at once
and exactly once
very many times.
I did the thing if you want to save them
up for yourself and replay them,
then I need some sort of persistence
level and the ability to kind of of get
those things back. But beyond that, you
wouldn't need it, in my opinion. As a
sort of break it down in terms of the
messaging patterns used to receive the
live prices, you would use the at most
once delivery of pub/sub because you can
send it to, you know, hundreds,
thousands of clients. And if they
millions and if they they miss some,
it's okay because they probably just
want to see whatever's the last one. So
if they dropped like, you know, 10 of
them in between, it's fine. Well, it's
not only just fine, it's actually
better. And again, you you have to
think, what do I actually want to see if
I know So I want to see if I'm I think
I'm connected, obviously. And if I'm
connected, I better see what the exact
price is now, not what it was 5 minutes
ago. Right. And to have the history of
the prices of these these stocks, you
would make use of NATS streaming. And we
we had a show on
streaming architecture before, and we've
also had a show on Kafka before. And
basically, all of these messages of the
different prices, they would be stored
within NATS. And if a client at a later
point decided they wanted to get a graph
of the history, they could replay the
messages that are stored in the stream
to get the history. And then finally for
the the buying and the selling orders,
they could use the request reply
functionality
of NATS. And because it's at most once
delivery,
if a client sends the request and they
don't get a response back, then the
client can assume that their order was
not processed and the application can
have the responsibility of making the
request again, rather than having that
sort of be handled by the messaging
system itself.
Almost correct. If you don't get
anything back, you don't really know
what happened.
Okay. If you get something back, you
either know it has succeeded or it
failed.
But again, I think the application and
again, I would ask the audience to put
their selves in front of their browser
doing online banking. What are the
patterns that you're doing, right? So,
if you get the I click on it and I got
an error back from Wells Fargo, you know
what that means. If you click and you
say it's deposited, you also know what
that means. If the page just goes blank,
you have to deal with that. What do you
do, right? And and that what I think
should be managed inside of applications
because again, you're just removing
yourself. So, what happens if the
messaging system blows up or or doesn't
respond to you? It's the same thing. You
have to do the same exact, you know,
error handling, failure scenario
handling as if you just sent it all the
way to the trading desk. Now, of course,
if the trading desk isn't online and
it's the middle of the night, let's say,
and it's old school,
you might use something like not
streaming or Kafka to say, "No, save
this and deliver it to them when they
come online."
But in today's world, that is the
exception these days. I mean,
everything's online all the time and you
know I'm talking directly to them even
if it's not trading hours. They will
say, "Got it, put it in the database,
you're good."
You know, hopefully that makes sense to
the audience. So, we we've moved to more
of an online, real-time, but there is
the need for these higher qualities of
service and saving things and maybe
replaying them for analysis or or
machine learning or data lakes or
business analytics, you know, Hadoop
type stuff. I do believe those exist for
sure, but I usually see them as as kind
of a hey, let's plug this thing in and
not affect anything that's going on and
start taking advantage of this, not
making it I'm just trying to send a
request to Jeremy. Why are you making me
use all this crazy complex stuff? It's
slow. I can send 40 messages a second or
whatever and the latency is really bad
and you know, so it almost becomes an
anti-pattern if you start there, but you
should also pick a technology that
allows you to grow and add these things
on without ever changing or perturbing
what already exists. My last question
would be related to the the streaming
functionality of NATS.
There's a lot of listeners who I'm sure
are familiar with Kafka to be used as an
event store. What kind of niche does
NATS fill in comparison to Kafka? Is is
it the simpler deployment or are there
things that are in Kafka that are not in
NATS? Like how would someone make that
decision? Yeah.
Yeah, so we're seeing a a tremendous
uptake, believe it or not, um where
there is a need for something like
streaming, but they want something
that's very easy to set up, develop
against, and run in production. And so,
we've seen quite a few opportunities
where um there is a large presence of
Kafka, but they want, you know, an
additional and technology that might be
a little bit lighter weight, but is
still as performant and still as fast,
and still can store as much data type
stuff. And so, we've seen a tremendous
amount of inbound interest that way. We
don't have the ecosystem that Kafka
does. We don't have all of the
connectors, they're all the different
subsystems.
And we don't have the the things that
that companies like Confluent do where
they have like KSQL. Um but for me, if
you're trying to do something like SQL,
then that exists. Dig into database and
you've got SQL. You've got real SQL. You
don't need um something that's built on
top of of something else. So, we've seen
a lot of and conversations, meaning
Kafka and NATS streaming and NATS as
kind of a
a supplementary or or additional
technology. And so, to that end, we've
actually started, and we've been known
as NATS for about 6 months, designing
kind of the successor to streaming. But
it's still philosophically going to hold
on to those, how do we even make it
simpler from a development standpoint,
but have the multiple patterns, make it
closer to NATS core, but it is secured
by default. It does understand all the
NATS 2.0 stuff like accounts and
sandboxes and sharing and all that other
stuff. And so, we're really excited
about that and where that's going. Um
but we believe
operational ease, maintenance, scaling,
um secure by default, multi-tenancy,
secure multi-tenancy by default,
multiple message patterns, multiple
QoS's, but in extremely simple, don't
need to read much, you know, I I
it we are not like this, but this is our
goal, which was the early days when when
Jobs returned Apple and there was no
manual. So, a lot of the stuff you did,
you would open it up and it would be
like step one, step two, step three,
step four, and you're done. That's a you
know, no one can do that as well as as
they did, per se, but that's kind of our
goal, which is how do we make this drop
dead easy from a day one development
through production, through all of the
other things that compromise production.
And we think there's a massive market
for for that to combine that with
larger, maybe technologies like you
know, Kafka and then Hadoop and then the
new machine learning and serverless and
all these other things. And uh we
especially think for for serverless and
being able to say this thing can be
running anywhere. We want to run it in
an instant, but we also still want
security and all these other things.
Uh again, most people are saying we're
trying to figure out how to spin this
thing up as fast as possible, but you're
still connecting to it through HTTP. And
uh we do have a bunch of serverless
function technologies out there that
that that we work with that they are
using NATS and NATS streaming to power
those and they're starting to see uh a
good amount of uptake. And again, it's
not
as much something that we, the NATS
team, are doing, per se. I think it's
the the market in general going, "Hey,
we want to look at these things cuz
they're different, make us think
differently, and we're innovating, but
we also want something that's just
simple and just works."
And so, we're starting to see a lot of
people keep saying that we came to you
because we just need something that is
simple and works. And um so, that's what
we're going to keep pushing for. I want
to close out and ask you, are there any
questions you think I should have asked
or something you would just like to say
to our audience? No, I think they they
were all great. I really appreciate the
time. I know
uh we've gone long, um but uh this is um
this pattern is very common. Meaning
I've I've done a lot of these with
customers and they go, "We'll allocate
about 2 hours." The the the most extreme
case was it went for a day and a half.
It's it's an amazing topic to explore
and see how we've moved, not just us as
a technology, but just in general.
And to talk about where we think things
are going and how we can meet and and
drive some of those uh those
innovations, um but to get something
that's
you know, a common communication thing,
it's secure by default, it's not a lot
of, you know, pain to get it to be
secure, right? Um
it has these notions of these containers
and sandboxes, but also promote sharing
in a secure way, and you know, a lot of
people have really the light bulb goes
off very fast for them, faster than I've
seen before. I've had technologies
before where I would be talking for
years
to to customers trying to say, "No, this
is a better way maybe to look at this
problem." And what I think I'm seeing
here is is that the market's figuring
that out for themselves, and it makes my
job trying to say what we've done about
it or what we think
about things and where they're going a
lot easier. And it's been really
exciting for me, you know, but I I've
been doing this for quite a long time,
but seeing the customers kind of go,
"Oh, wait a minute, we could think of
it, you know, like this." The again,
having their own Tesla moment uh is
really exciting for not only us and and
and uh you know, being the the NATS core
team, but the whole ecosystem and
and just technology in general. It's
it's really exciting to be able to see
all of the changes that are going on and
and realize that the next 10 years will
probably eclipse the last 50, right? In
terms of progress across the board, and
uh
uh yeah, we just want to be uh a teeny
little piece of that if possible. Yeah,
I think, you know, as a developer,
there's there's so many things for
people to learn and if we could at least
cut down on some of it, you know, from
the ops perspective, from the
development perspective, I think that's
a win for everyone. So, that's exciting.
How can people follow you on the
internet? Uh so, Twitter, Derek
Collison, d e r e k c o l l i s o n,
Derek@nats.io
if you want to send me an email. Nats.io
will get you to like our Slack channels
and Google Groups and uh
I think we have about 1,500 people on
Slack or so. So, we're vastly not known,
but the people who do know us are very
passionate like we are about the tech
and how you apply it. Um so, come join
us, ask us questions,
um send me an email if you want
directly, tell me what I'm wrong about.
Um no problems whatsoever and and again,
thank you, Jeremy. I really appreciate
the the time. Yeah, this has been a a
fantastic discussion. Thank you so much
for coming on the show, Derek. This is
Jeremy Jung for Software Engineering
Radio. Thank you for listening.
Digital Ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy, manage, and scale
applications of any size, removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love.
Digital Ocean stands out from the crowd
due to its simplicity, high performance,
and no billing surprises.
Join a community of over 3.5 million
developers on Digital Ocean. Sign up
with a free credit at do.co/seradio.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE-Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.